<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Case Study | Aleksey Nozdryn-Plotnicki]]></title>
  <link href="http://alekseynp.com/categories/case-study/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alekseynp.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-16T13:24:12-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://alekseynp.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aleksey Nozdryn-Plotnicki]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Analysis of the Determinants of Selling Price for Vancouver NHL Ticket Auctions]]></title>
    <link href="http://alekseynp.com/2014/02/15/analysis-of-the-determinants-of-selling-price-for-vancouver-nhl-ticket-auctions/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-15T20:11:10-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alekseynp.com/2014/02/15/analysis-of-the-determinants-of-selling-price-for-vancouver-nhl-ticket-auctions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1>Introduction</h1>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been scraping a lot lately. If data is the new oil, then it&rsquo;s time I started pumping it. I came across this old project of mine from a statistics course in my masters program, dated December 15, 2006. Stubhub today should be a goldmine of data and I hope appropriate data and/or analysis is being passed to the leagues to help them set prices.</p>

<blockquote>**Analysis of the determinants of selling price for Vancouver NHL ticket auctions**

Data was collected for a one month period of auctions completed on eBay, a popular internet auction site, for tickets to see the Vancouver Canucks play at home.  The data was analyzed to determine a good regression model for the selling price per ticket. The most significant indicator was face value, but auctions by sellers with higher feedback scores and transactions that are completed longer before a game also finished with a higher price per ticket. Noteworthy insignificant factors were number of tickets in a lot, the feedback percentage rating for the seller, and the length of the auction.</blockquote>


<h1>Findings</h1>

<p>My most interesting finding would provide guidance to price setting.</p>

<blockquote>Of most interest is the regular game Upper Bowl IV and Upper Bowl V price categories. The eBay market price difference from Ticketmaster is significant and in the case of Upper Bowl V seats, sizable. This indicates that these tickets are priced well below market demand. It would seem that from the consumer’s perspective Upper Bowl IV and V are indistinguishable and the Canucks should seriously consider charging more for these seats.</blockquote>


<p>I also found that:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Tickets sold further ahead of game day sold for more. There is a fundamental tension in the market for tickets, a time-valued good (after game day a ticket is worth zero). Some shoppers are will pass on an auction hoping to find a better deal later. Some shoppers are willing to pay more for the certainty of having a ticket now. Some sellers want to unload their tickets now before they become worthless. Some sellers will patiently wait out the buyers in order to fetch a higher price. In my data there was a correlation of 0.3 between minimum bid and time until game day. This is evidence  of patient sellers setting and getting higher prices further ahead of game day.</p></li>
<li><p>Feedback rating was a more important factor than feedback percentage. In the marketplace that I studied where most operators were small-scale with 100% positive feedback, their tickets sold at a higher price if they gathered more positive feedback. On the flip-side, big-time operators with only a little less than 100% feedback did not suffer greatly.</p></li>
<li><p>The number of tickets in a lot did not affect selling price per ticket. You would expect four tickets together to be worth more than two separate pairs, and surely they are, but there was not enough evidence in the data, so it is not a strong impact.</p></li>
<li><p>Length of the auction did not have an effect. Longer auctions presumably get seen by more people and therefore sell for more, unless the market is active enough such that a critical mass of buyers will see auctions of short length.</p></li>
</ul>


<h2></h2>

<h1>How I Did It</h1>

<ol>
<li><p> A scraper was written in C# to collect html pages from eBay of completed auctions for Vancouver Canucks tickets</p></li>
<li><p> Extensive regular expression matching was done on the auction&rsquo;s free text in order to determine what game the tickets were for, how many tickets there were, and other factors like where the seats were in the stadium</p></li>
<li><p> Regression models were tried in order to find a good fit</p></li>
<li><p> Regression coefficients were interpreted to draw conclusions</p></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Case Study: Visualizing the Taxonomy of an Organisation's Activities in Strategy/profitability Projects at a Global Organisation]]></title>
    <link href="http://alekseynp.com/2013/07/08/case-study-visualizing-the-taxonomy-of-an-organisations-activities-in-strategyprofitability-projects-at-a-global-organisation/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-08T16:41:30-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alekseynp.com/2013/07/08/case-study-visualizing-the-taxonomy-of-an-organisations-activities-in-strategyprofitability-projects-at-a-global-organisation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Example visual
<a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/activity_taxonomy.png"><img src="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/activity_taxonomy-300x300.png" alt="activity_taxonomy" /></a>
Note: Sample content merely for demonstration.</p>

<p><strong>The Content</strong>
The activities of an organisation were broken down into four levels of taxonomy.</p>

<p><strong>Context</strong>
The organisation was preparing to deliver strategy and profitability projects.</p>

<p><strong>What we did</strong>
Simply put, we took the taxonomy and built the visual.</p>

<p><strong>Benefits</strong>
With good reason, it is important to Strategy people that the concrete actions recommended by their work are underpinned by a good theoretical/abstract structure. This visual shows that structure giving everyone sight and confidence in it. Consultancies, often in the marketplace, often in white papers, want to show a completeness of vision and this did just that.</p>

<p>The taxonomy along with it&rsquo;s visual were useful for:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>the project planning, structuring, and approval stage</p></li>
<li><p>project delivery, as activities could be build around the structure, and tracked against it</p></li>
<li><p>Take completeness of vision to completeness of execution</p></li>
</ul>


<p>The condensed, all-in-one-page visual also supported development of the taxonomy. Workshops, edits and revisions were all facilitated by the visualisation. Otherwise people were restricted linear text, emails, Excel sheets, and other unwieldy mediums where duplications and missing items were hard to find.</p>

<p><strong>Make your own</strong></p>

<p>I have previously published tools to the web for generating visuals of hierarchical data:</p>

<table style="font-size:10px; border-spacing:30px;" >
  <tr >
    
<td style="text-align:center; vertical-align:top; border:1px solid #dddddd; padding:10px; margin:2px; border-radius:6px 6px 6px 6px;" >[![](http://alekseynp.github.io/portfolio/images/info_wheel_4_alpha_icon.png)  
Info Wheel  
(4-level)](http://alekseynp.github.io/portfolio/create-visualisations/infowheel4/infoWheel.html)
</td>
    
<td style="text-align:center; vertical-align:top; border:1px solid #dddddd; padding:10px; margin:2px; border-radius:6px 6px 6px 6px;" >[![](http://alekseynp.github.io/portfolio/images/node_tree_4_alpha_icon.png)  
Radial Tree  
(4-level)](http://alekseynp.github.io/portfolio/create-visualisations/reingold-Tilford_Tree4/Reingold_Tilford_Tree.html)
</td>
  </tr>
</table>


<p>I will publish more on special request.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Case Study: Visualizing the Process Model in a Siebel Implementation at a Public Sector Organisation]]></title>
    <link href="http://alekseynp.com/2013/07/06/case-study-visualizing-the-process-model-in-a-siebel-implementation-at-a-public-sector-organisation/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-06T16:37:20-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alekseynp.com/2013/07/06/case-study-visualizing-the-process-model-in-a-siebel-implementation-at-a-public-sector-organisation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Example visual
<a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/process_model.png"><img src="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/process_model-265x300.png" alt="process_model" /></a>
Note: Sample content merely for demonstration.</p>

<p><strong>The Content</strong>
Business processes more or less broken down into Level 1, Level 2, Level 3, Level 4</p>

<p><strong>Context</strong>
The client was designing a brand new set of business processes to go in hand with a brand new implementation of Oracle Siebel &ndash;  a Customer Relationship Management (CRM) system. Customers have accounts, things they need from us, things we need from them, processes to go through, etc. Go-live was approaching and confidence was low.</p>

<p><strong>What we did</strong>
We generated an A0 (for North Americans, this is more or less 4x4 regular sheets of paper) circular visual of all of the processes being implemented in Siebel and put it up on the wall in the primary open-office space.</p>

<p><strong>Benefits</strong>
On a single page we were able to both show that:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>The problem was not infinite, could be counted, and could fit on a single, if large, piece of paper</p></li>
<li><p>There were indeed very many processes, and the size and complexity of what had been accomplished to-date was something the entire team could be proud of</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Processes could be highlighted, coloured, or ticked-off to track progress.</p>

<p><strong>Make your own</strong></p>

<p>I have previously published tools to the web for generating visuals of hierarchical data:</p>

<table style="font-size:10px; border-spacing:30px;" >
  <tr >
    
<td style="text-align:center; vertical-align:top; border:1px solid #dddddd; padding:10px; margin:2px; border-radius:6px 6px 6px 6px;" >[![](http://alekseynp.github.io/portfolio/images/info_wheel_4_alpha_icon.png)  
Info Wheel  
(4-level)](http://alekseynp.github.io/portfolio/create-visualisations/infowheel4/infoWheel.html)
</td>
    
<td style="text-align:center; vertical-align:top; border:1px solid #dddddd; padding:10px; margin:2px; border-radius:6px 6px 6px 6px;" >[![](http://alekseynp.github.io/portfolio/images/node_tree_4_alpha_icon.png)  
Radial Tree  
(4-level)](http://alekseynp.github.io/portfolio/create-visualisations/reingold-Tilford_Tree4/Reingold_Tilford_Tree.html)
</td>
  </tr>
</table>


<p>I will publish more on special request.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Case Study: Visualizing the Data Model in a Business Intelligence Change Program at a Global Manufacturer/retailer/distributor]]></title>
    <link href="http://alekseynp.com/2013/07/04/case-study-visualizing-the-data-model-in-a-business-intelligence-change-program-at-a-global-manufacturerretailerdistributor/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-04T16:33:16-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alekseynp.com/2013/07/04/case-study-visualizing-the-data-model-in-a-business-intelligence-change-program-at-a-global-manufacturerretailerdistributor</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Example visual
<a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/data_model.png"><img src="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/data_model-300x300.png" alt="data_model" /></a>
Note: Sample content merely for demonstration.</p>

<p><strong>The Content</strong>
The information model, structured as business function at level 1, entity at level 2, and data field at level 3.</p>

<p><strong>Context</strong>
This global manufacturer/retailer/distributor was engaged in a program to update their Business Intelligence including their information model.</p>

<p>The client prized communication that was innovative, on a single-page, and not PowerPoint.</p>

<p><strong>What we did</strong>
Made the visual, shared it, printed it and put it up on the wall.</p>

<p><strong>Benefits</strong>
The visual was able to show people not just what the content of the information model was, but what an information model is. An idea that was only in a few people&rsquo;s heads was made concrete and accessible to others. In some ways those colours and that shape were an information model.</p>

<p>An abstract idea made physical, the visual facilitated meetings, as people could literally walk up to it and point at what things they were talking about.</p>

<p>By seeing it all in one place, people could realize what was missing and what was overlapping. Outstanding issues of data stewardship/ownership (i.e. What single level 1 category items belonged under) were out in the open where everyone could see, not lost in some kind of Excel issue tracker or somebody&rsquo;s meeting minutes. Who owns sales turnover, Finance or Sales? Sales turnover should appear only once in the visual under only one of the two level 1 categories.</p>

<p><strong>Make your own</strong></p>

<p>I have previously published tools to the web for generating visuals of hierarchical data:</p>

<table style="font-size:10px; border-spacing:30px;" >
  <tr >
    
<td style="text-align:center; vertical-align:top; border:1px solid #dddddd; padding:10px; margin:2px; border-radius:6px 6px 6px 6px;" >[![](http://alekseynp.github.io/portfolio/images/info_wheel_4_alpha_icon.png)  
Info Wheel  
(4-level)](http://alekseynp.github.io/portfolio/create-visualisations/infowheel4/infoWheel.html)
</td>
    
<td style="text-align:center; vertical-align:top; border:1px solid #dddddd; padding:10px; margin:2px; border-radius:6px 6px 6px 6px;" >[![](http://alekseynp.github.io/portfolio/images/node_tree_4_alpha_icon.png)  
Radial Tree  
(4-level)](http://alekseynp.github.io/portfolio/create-visualisations/reingold-Tilford_Tree4/Reingold_Tilford_Tree.html)
</td>
  </tr>
</table>


<p>I will publish more on special request.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Communication in Consulting: Circular Visuals of Hierarchical Information]]></title>
    <link href="http://alekseynp.com/2013/07/02/communication-in-consulting-circular-visuals-of-hierarchical-information/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-02T16:28:15-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alekseynp.com/2013/07/02/communication-in-consulting-circular-visuals-of-hierarchical-information</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Consultants need to communicate all of the time, and that isn&rsquo;t always making PowerPoint slides, though it can sometimes seem like it. Technical consultants often wrestle with surprisingly abstract concepts in fields unfamiliar to their client or parts of the client&rsquo;s organisation. While a consultant&rsquo;s role is partly to shield their client from that complexity, there will also be times where things must be shared with a wider audience.</p>

<p>One such abstraction that comes up again and again is a hierarchical structure or taxonomy of information. This is where an idea is broken down into categories, sub-categories and so on. These structures are often used in order to:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Ensure completeness – no item or category is missing</p></li>
<li><p>Break work down into manageable chunks – Work through a project one sub-category at a time</p></li>
<li><p>Organize an otherwise unwieldy collection of ideas – Bring structure to the problem (a skill highly prized in consulting job interviews)</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Case Studies</strong></p>

<p>Here are three applications that I have seen or been involved in&hellip;</p>

<p><strong>1. Data model</strong></p>

<p>Context: Business Intelligence change program
Organisation: Global manufacturer/retailer/distributor
<a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/data_model.png"><img src="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/data_model-300x300.png" alt="data_model" /></a>
Note: Sample content merely for demonstration.
Read more: <a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/2013/07/04/case-study-visualizing-the-data-model-in-a-business-intelligence-change-program-at-a-global-manufacturerretailerdistributor/">Case study</a></p>

<p><strong>2. Process model</strong></p>

<p>Context: Siebel implementation
Organisation: Public sector organisation
<a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/process_model.png"><img src="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/process_model-265x300.png" alt="process_model" /></a>
Note: Sample content merely for demonstration.
Read more: <a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/2013/07/06/case-study-visualizing-the-process-model-in-a-siebel-implementation-at-a-public-sector-organisation/">Case study</a></p>

<p><strong>3.  Taxonomy of organisation&rsquo;s activities</strong></p>

<p>Context: Strategy/profitability projects
Organisation: Global organisation
<a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/activity_taxonomy.png"><img src="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/activity_taxonomy-300x300.png" alt="activity_taxonomy" /></a>
Note: Sample content merely for demonstration.
Read more: <a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/2013/07/08/case-study-visualizing-the-taxonomy-of-an-organisations-activities-in-strategyprofitability-projects-at-a-global-organisation/">Case study</a></p>

<p><strong>Circular layouts</strong></p>

<p>Circular or radial layouts are unpopular in data viz and for good reasons. When data is involved, the space, distance, size, and angles generally undermine the effectiveness of the visualisations. However, when only categorical information is present (i.e. no numbers) there are some significant benefits:</p>

<p>All on one page – It&rsquo;s critical that stuff fit all on a single page – large pages if necessary. Long Excel spreadsheet logs with columns like Category, Sub-Category, Sub-Sub-Category, Item, Description, Status are useful structures for managing complex work, but totally useless for communication. Radial layouts take tree-shaped information that would otherwise be a long and narrow list, and utilizes the horizontal space of the page, to wrap up the tail and bring it all onto a single sheet.</p>

<p>Engaging – In consulting it&rsquo;s important that your communication be engaging. You want as much support from your client&rsquo;s organisation behind your work as possible. You must win this at every opportunity from each individual who has their normal job that already consumes all of their time and energy and probably doesn&rsquo;t find your work as interesting as you do. Circular layouts look good, and this is important. You want someone to see it, say “Hey, what&rsquo;s that?”, and a take a step forward to have a closer look.</p>

<p><strong>Make your own</strong></p>

<p>I have previously published tools to the web for generating visuals of hierarchical data:</p>

<table style="font-size: 10px; border-spacing: 30px;" >
<tbody >
<tr >

<td style="text-align: center; vertical-align: top; border: 1px solid #dddddd; padding: 10px; margin: 2px; border-radius: 6px 6px 6px 6px;" >[![](http://alekseynp.github.io/portfolio/images/info_wheel_4_alpha_icon.png)
Info Wheel
(4-level)](http://alekseynp.github.io/portfolio/create-visualisations/infowheel4/infoWheel.html)
</td>

<td style="text-align: center; vertical-align: top; border: 1px solid #dddddd; padding: 10px; margin: 2px; border-radius: 6px 6px 6px 6px;" >[![](http://alekseynp.github.io/portfolio/images/node_tree_4_alpha_icon.png)
Radial Tree
(4-level)](http://alekseynp.github.io/portfolio/create-visualisations/reingold-Tilford_Tree4/Reingold_Tilford_Tree.html)
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>I will publish more on special request.</p>

<p>Sure you could generate these visuals by hand in PowerPoint, and indeed many junior consultants are probably re-doing just that until 11 pm at night every time something changes. As much as they think they are gaining from the appearance of dedication that this creates, there must be a better way.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
