<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Data Journalism | Aleksey Nozdryn-Plotnicki]]></title>
  <link href="http://alekseynp.com/categories/data-journalism/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alekseynp.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-16T13:24:12-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://alekseynp.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aleksey Nozdryn-Plotnicki]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Ontario Sunshine List Work in the CBC News]]></title>
    <link href="http://alekseynp.com/2014/04/01/my-ontario-sunshine-list-work-in-the-cbc-news/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-01T12:13:29-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alekseynp.com/2014/04/01/my-ontario-sunshine-list-work-in-the-cbc-news</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just some shameless self-promotion. You can find my work cited in the CBC News from today.</p>

<p>Kazi Stastna writes <a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/sunshine-list-2014-ontario-s-list-drives-salaries-up-not-down-1.2592793">Sunshine List 2014: Ontario&rsquo;s list drives salaries up, not down</a> and includes:</p>

<blockquote>Ontario pathologists did just that and saw their Sunshine List salaries increase by 20 to 25 per cent between 2011 and 2012, compared with the 2.2 per cent average for the list as a whole, according to an [analysis](http://alekseynp.github.io/2013/04/19/20-25-raise-for-ontarios-pathologists-in-201-shows-sunshine-list/) done by data blogger Aleksey Nozdryn-Plotnicki.

&#8230;

Nozdryn-Plotnicki [found](http://alekseynp.github.io/2013/04/19/7-2-raise-for-1000-best-paid-ontario-public-sector-employees/) that this inflationary effect is greatest at the upper echelons of the Sunshine List, with the salaries of the 1,000 highest-paid workers rising 7.2 per cent between 2011 and 2012, compared with 2.2 per cent for the bottom half of the list.</blockquote>


<p>They are, of course, referring to my work:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/2013/04/19/7-2-raise-for-1000-best-paid-ontario-public-sector-employees/">7.2% raise for 1,000 best paid Ontario public sector employees</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/2013/04/19/20-25-raise-for-ontarios-pathologists-in-201-shows-sunshine-list/">20-25% raise for Ontario’s pathologists in 2012
</a></p></li>
</ul>


<p>For those outside of Canada, the CBC, the Canadian Broadcasting Corporation is a public entity and major player in the Canadian news media market. It&rsquo;s my personal number one source for Canadian news.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I Tried to Sell Open Government Data]]></title>
    <link href="http://alekseynp.com/2014/03/28/i-tried-to-sell-open-government-data/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-28T22:13:28-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alekseynp.com/2014/03/28/i-tried-to-sell-open-government-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I tried to sell open government data, but I won&rsquo;t be the only one.</p>

<p>In 2013 I wrote a series of data journalism articles on the topic of <a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/topic-ontario-public-salary-disclosure/">Ontario Public Sector Salary Disclosure</a>. The posts were based on data made available as part of a disclosure initiative in the Canadian province of Ontario. Data was published freely and openly on the Ontario Ministry of Finance website in html and pdf format. I performed a convoluted scraping and processing exercise to build a definitive, unified data set and then performed some analysis in order to identify some interesting headlines.</p>

<p>In late 2013 I was approached by someone who was looking for the data behind my analysis. I agreed to share the data on a few conditions, one of which was non-commercial use that they were unable to meet. And so I offered to sell them the data. Free, open, public data.</p>

<blockquote>Sorry Aleksey. Not going to pay for public data even if private hours went into scraping it.</blockquote>


<p>I knew I had entered a moral landscape with shades of grey on a topic that people would be emotional about.</p>

<p>Government data should be free and open! After all it&rsquo;s our data for us! Well except perhaps in instances where user fees would be a more appropriate measure to spread the cost of data production more proportionally to those who will benefit. And the shades are grey.</p>

<p>My simplest and most direct defense is: My customer knew that the data was freely available, but I still had something to sell them.</p>

<p>Nobody owns the truth, but once they have measured it, processed it, and made it available in a useful format, then they have something that they could sell to you. If I sold you a map based on free government data or delivered you a service based on it, you would accept that.</p>

<p>I wrote about the <a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/2013/05/28/data-sins-of-the-ontario-ministry-of-finance-public-sector-salary-disclosure/">Data Sins of the Ontario Ministry of Finance – Public Sector Salary Disclosure</a> and <a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/2013/04/22/current-publishing-of-ontario-sunshine-list-not-good-enough/">Current publishing of Ontario “Sunshine List” not good enough</a>. This data was &ldquo;open&rdquo; but not truly &ldquo;open&rdquo; and it required considerable effort to process before I could analyse it.</p>

<p><strong>ProPublica</strong></p>

<p>Why I wrote this today rather than continue to procrastinate is that I saw this: <a href="http://www.propublica.org/article/introducing-the-propublica-data-store">Introducing the ProPublica Data Store</a></p>

<blockquote>For datasets that are the result of significant expenditures of our time and effort, we&#8217;re charging a reasonable one-time fee: In most cases, it&#8217;s $200 for journalists and $2,000 for academic researchers. Those wanting to use data commercially should reach out to us to discuss pricing.</blockquote>


<p>And relevantly, they have data sets for sale based on data acquired through the American Freedom of Information Act.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Which Countries Are Successfully Requesting Data From Facebook?]]></title>
    <link href="http://alekseynp.com/2013/08/29/which-countries-are-successfully-requesting-data-from-facebook/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-29T11:33:42-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alekseynp.com/2013/08/29/which-countries-are-successfully-requesting-data-from-facebook</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/facebook_requests_v1_publish.png"><img src="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/facebook_requests_v1_publish.png" alt="facebook_requests_v1_publish" /></a></p>

<p>Recently <a href="http://newsroom.fb.com/News/699/Global-Government-Requests-Report">Facebook published a report</a> covering the first 6 months of 2013, disclosing which countries have made data requests from Facebook, and to what proportion of requests did Facebook respond with at least some data. &ldquo;Transparency and trust are core values at Facebook.&rdquo; And good on them for at least trying not to be evil. Unfortunately, in this case &ldquo;transparency&rdquo; has amounted to a single HTML table with 71 rows of data. Given the enormous audience for this information, perhaps some data visualisation would have been appropriate. After all, what is &ldquo;transparency&rdquo; if people can&rsquo;t really &ldquo;see&rdquo; the data?</p>

<p><strong>Proportionality - Requests vs. Facebook Population</strong></p>

<p>I was going to combine the requests data with Facebook populations, but it <a href="http://www.motherjones.com/kevin-drum/2013/08/chart-day-which-countries-snoop-facebook-users-most">looks like this has already been done</a>. This is a classic example of the importance of relative ratios in data reporting and journalism. The result is also important given the position of Germany in the current debate on web privacy. I encourage you to take a look <a href="http://www.motherjones.com/kevin-drum/2013/08/chart-day-which-countries-snoop-facebook-users-most">here</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Successful Requests</strong></p>

<p>Facebook tells us that it is battling hard against any and all requests, and that it only complies with the strict letter of the law. Still it would be interesting to see which countries are more successful than others. We could do this simply by looking at the success ratio in the report, but plotting it against number of requests adds an interesting dimension.</p>

<p>Without being an expert in online data privacy and international law, it&rsquo;s interesting to note a few things:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>In the bottom left, countries who have made few requests with very little success</p></li>
<li><p>In the top-right, countries who have made a lot of requests with good success</p>

<ul>
<li><p>United States, United Kingdom, and Australia leading the pack</p></li>
<li><p>Canada not together with those nations above</p></li>
<li><p>Italy, France, Germany, Spain, Portugal clustered - Western Schengen</p></li>
<li><p>Switzerland and Austria with much lower success rates than those nations above</p></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>Poland a proliferate requester with remarkably little success</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Meta</strong></p>

<p>Logarithmic scales are probably not the best practice in data journalism, but it was worth it in order to spread out the dots and see the different countries.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Ontario Sunshine List Work in the Financial Post]]></title>
    <link href="http://alekseynp.com/2013/07/28/my-ontario-sunshine-list-work-in-the-financial-post/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-28T01:30:10-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alekseynp.com/2013/07/28/my-ontario-sunshine-list-work-in-the-financial-post</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A little late posting this, but you can find my work cited in the Financial Post from July 13.</p>

<p>Terence Corcoran writes <a href="http://opinion.financialpost.com/2013/07/08/terence-corcoran-the-sunshine-race-to-the-top/">The sunshine race to the to</a> and includes:</p>

<blockquote>&#8220;A quick and dirty snapshot of trends was recently highlighted by statistical blogger Aleksey Nozdryn-Plotnicki. Following release of the 2013 Ontario sunshine list, Mr. Nozdryn-Plotnicki’s posted a graph that showed big increases in the salaries of the province’s top 1000 income earners (see graph below). The highest paid individuals in the province recorded wage gains of 7.2% during 2012 “where everyone else saw 2.2%,” said Mr. Nozdryn-Plotnicki in a posting on his site, thinkdatavis.com. One year doesn’t make a trend, but similarly shaped graphs can be found for 2008, 2006, 2004 and 2000.

Another graphic example from thinkdatavis.com: Ontario’s pathologist salaries have increased 5.5% annually since 1996. During the first decade following the sunshine laws, pathologist packages increased 6.6% annually. That was followed by a four-year flat period. Then, in 2012, the pathologists recorded a single-year gain of 22%.&#8221;</blockquote>


<p>For those outside Canada, the Financial Post is a part of the National Post and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_newspapers_in_Canada_by_circulation">according to Wikipedia</a> had a weekly circulation of 800,000 in 2011.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Sun Shines Fondly on Ontario University Presidents]]></title>
    <link href="http://alekseynp.com/2013/07/12/the-sun-shines-fondly-on-ontario-university-presidents/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-12T21:10:01-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alekseynp.com/2013/07/12/the-sun-shines-fondly-on-ontario-university-presidents</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since 1996, the ten best paid Ontario university presidents have seen their packages increased on average about 5.1% annually. This compares to:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>4.0% for the 10,000th best paid person on the Sunshine List since 2001 (when there first were 10,000 names on the list)</p></li>
<li><p>3.5% annually for the 20,000th best paid since 2004</p></li>
<li><p>5.5% annually for Pathologists since 1996</p></li>
</ul>


<p>While not as shocking as the single-year 22% raise that I <a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/2013/04/19/20-25-raise-for-ontarios-pathologists-in-201-shows-sunshine-list/">previously identified for pathologists</a>, this is evidence that university presidents are in the elite club for whom the sun shines strongly. As I have <a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/2013/05/06/second-largest-growth-gap-in-2012-for-ontario-sunshine-list/">shown previously</a>, those at the top in Ontario not only higher salaries, and bigger raises in absolute dollars, but also larger percentage increases annually which compound and lead to bigger gap between them and everyone else.</p>

<p>Explore the data below:</p>

<p><a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/university-presidents.png"><img src="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/university-presidents.png" alt="university presidents" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Questions and Answers</strong></p>

<p>Why are there sudden dips in the lines?</p>

<p>For example, Brock in 2007 and Carleton in 2006 and 2009. When an outgoing or incoming president works only a portion of a year, they earn less and are reported as less.</p>

<p>Why is there missing years sometimes?</p>

<p>As with sudden dips in the lines, if both the outgoing and incoming presidents work only a portion of the year and only earn less than $100,000, they will not qualify for disclosure and there will be no data for them. Also in some years the data may be outright missing.</p>

<p>Why is there almost no data for Queen’s?</p>

<p>I struggled to identify presidents of Queen’s in the data. Perhaps their structure is different. I took Daniel R. Woolf, Principal - Principal&rsquo;s Office for 2013, and Wade G. Hall, Executive Director Development for 2010 and 2009, but this is probably wrong. Any experts on the structure can feel free to inform me and I can make the appropriate correction.</p>

<p>Why do many lines start after 1997?</p>

<p>Before this period, the given presidents did not earn more than $100,000 and did not qualify for disclosure.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
