<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Canada | Aleksey Nozdryn-Plotnicki]]></title>
  <link href="http://alekseynp.com/categories/canada/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alekseynp.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-16T14:24:44-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://alekseynp.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aleksey Nozdryn-Plotnicki]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Ontario Sunshine List Work in the CBC News]]></title>
    <link href="http://alekseynp.com/2014/04/01/my-ontario-sunshine-list-work-in-the-cbc-news/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-01T12:13:29-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alekseynp.com/2014/04/01/my-ontario-sunshine-list-work-in-the-cbc-news</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just some shameless self-promotion. You can find my work cited in the CBC News from today.</p>

<p>Kazi Stastna writes <a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/sunshine-list-2014-ontario-s-list-drives-salaries-up-not-down-1.2592793">Sunshine List 2014: Ontario&rsquo;s list drives salaries up, not down</a> and includes:</p>

<blockquote>Ontario pathologists did just that and saw their Sunshine List salaries increase by 20 to 25 per cent between 2011 and 2012, compared with the 2.2 per cent average for the list as a whole, according to an [analysis](http://alekseynp.com/2013/04/19/20-25-raise-for-ontarios-pathologists-in-201-shows-sunshine-list/) done by data blogger Aleksey Nozdryn-Plotnicki.

&#8230;

Nozdryn-Plotnicki [found](http://alekseynp.com/2013/04/19/7-2-raise-for-1000-best-paid-ontario-public-sector-employees/) that this inflationary effect is greatest at the upper echelons of the Sunshine List, with the salaries of the 1,000 highest-paid workers rising 7.2 per cent between 2011 and 2012, compared with 2.2 per cent for the bottom half of the list.</blockquote>


<p>They are, of course, referring to my work:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://alekseynp.com/2013/04/19/7-2-raise-for-1000-best-paid-ontario-public-sector-employees/">7.2% raise for 1,000 best paid Ontario public sector employees</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://alekseynp.com/2013/04/19/20-25-raise-for-ontarios-pathologists-in-201-shows-sunshine-list/">20-25% raise for Ontario’s pathologists in 2012
</a></p></li>
</ul>


<p>For those outside of Canada, the CBC, the Canadian Broadcasting Corporation is a public entity and major player in the Canadian news media market. It&rsquo;s my personal number one source for Canadian news.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Ontario Sunshine List Work in the Financial Post]]></title>
    <link href="http://alekseynp.com/2013/07/28/my-ontario-sunshine-list-work-in-the-financial-post/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-28T01:30:10-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alekseynp.com/2013/07/28/my-ontario-sunshine-list-work-in-the-financial-post</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A little late posting this, but you can find my work cited in the Financial Post from July 13.</p>

<p>Terence Corcoran writes <a href="http://opinion.financialpost.com/2013/07/08/terence-corcoran-the-sunshine-race-to-the-top/">The sunshine race to the to</a> and includes:</p>

<blockquote>&#8220;A quick and dirty snapshot of trends was recently highlighted by statistical blogger Aleksey Nozdryn-Plotnicki. Following release of the 2013 Ontario sunshine list, Mr. Nozdryn-Plotnicki’s posted a graph that showed big increases in the salaries of the province’s top 1000 income earners (see graph below). The highest paid individuals in the province recorded wage gains of 7.2% during 2012 “where everyone else saw 2.2%,” said Mr. Nozdryn-Plotnicki in a posting on his site, thinkdatavis.com. One year doesn’t make a trend, but similarly shaped graphs can be found for 2008, 2006, 2004 and 2000.

Another graphic example from thinkdatavis.com: Ontario’s pathologist salaries have increased 5.5% annually since 1996. During the first decade following the sunshine laws, pathologist packages increased 6.6% annually. That was followed by a four-year flat period. Then, in 2012, the pathologists recorded a single-year gain of 22%.&#8221;</blockquote>


<p>For those outside Canada, the Financial Post is a part of the National Post and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_newspapers_in_Canada_by_circulation">according to Wikipedia</a> had a weekly circulation of 800,000 in 2011.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Sun Shines Fondly on Ontario University Presidents]]></title>
    <link href="http://alekseynp.com/2013/07/12/the-sun-shines-fondly-on-ontario-university-presidents/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-12T21:10:01-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alekseynp.com/2013/07/12/the-sun-shines-fondly-on-ontario-university-presidents</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since 1996, the ten best paid Ontario university presidents have seen their packages increased on average about 5.1% annually. This compares to:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>4.0% for the 10,000th best paid person on the Sunshine List since 2001 (when there first were 10,000 names on the list)</p></li>
<li><p>3.5% annually for the 20,000th best paid since 2004</p></li>
<li><p>5.5% annually for Pathologists since 1996</p></li>
</ul>


<p>While not as shocking as the single-year 22% raise that I <a href="http://alekseynp.com/2013/04/19/20-25-raise-for-ontarios-pathologists-in-201-shows-sunshine-list/">previously identified for pathologists</a>, this is evidence that university presidents are in the elite club for whom the sun shines strongly. As I have <a href="http://alekseynp.com/2013/05/06/second-largest-growth-gap-in-2012-for-ontario-sunshine-list/">shown previously</a>, those at the top in Ontario not only higher salaries, and bigger raises in absolute dollars, but also larger percentage increases annually which compound and lead to bigger gap between them and everyone else.</p>

<p>Explore the data below:</p>

<p><a href="http://alekseynp.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/university-presidents.png"><img src="http://alekseynp.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/university-presidents.png" alt="university presidents" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Questions and Answers</strong></p>

<p>Why are there sudden dips in the lines?</p>

<p>For example, Brock in 2007 and Carleton in 2006 and 2009. When an outgoing or incoming president works only a portion of a year, they earn less and are reported as less.</p>

<p>Why is there missing years sometimes?</p>

<p>As with sudden dips in the lines, if both the outgoing and incoming presidents work only a portion of the year and only earn less than $100,000, they will not qualify for disclosure and there will be no data for them. Also in some years the data may be outright missing.</p>

<p>Why is there almost no data for Queen’s?</p>

<p>I struggled to identify presidents of Queen’s in the data. Perhaps their structure is different. I took Daniel R. Woolf, Principal - Principal&rsquo;s Office for 2013, and Wade G. Hall, Executive Director Development for 2010 and 2009, but this is probably wrong. Any experts on the structure can feel free to inform me and I can make the appropriate correction.</p>

<p>Why do many lines start after 1997?</p>

<p>Before this period, the given presidents did not earn more than $100,000 and did not qualify for disclosure.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Data Sins of the Ontario Ministry of Finance – Public Sector Salary Disclosure]]></title>
    <link href="http://alekseynp.com/2013/05/27/data-sins-of-the-ontario-ministry-of-finance-public-sector-salary-disclosure/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-27T23:47:59-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alekseynp.com/2013/05/27/data-sins-of-the-ontario-ministry-of-finance-public-sector-salary-disclosure</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Upfront warning: This article is likely to be only interesting to two types of people, those expecting to work with this data from the Ontario Ministry of Finance, and anyone in a position to demand better.</p>

<p>Apart from their obvious failure to publish the data in clean, machine-readable formats like csv or xls, the Ontario Ministry of Finance is making other important mistakes when making releases for the Public Salary Disclosure.</p>

<p><strong>Addenda</strong></p>

<p>The addenda is inconsistently applied to the master, published, available data. For each year an addenda is published, containing changes to the data from when it was published. There are three types of changes: additions, changes, and deletions. As far as I can tell, deletions are acted upon, and are reflected in the published set (this is so for 2012), but changes and additions are not. This is a big problem, because now no clear audit trail exists for the data, and people using the data from different times will disagree on basic facts like the number of employees disclosed.</p>

<p>The inconsistent application of the addenda is also inconsistent. For instance, in 2009, the deletions have not be enacted upon the published data.</p>

<p>Changes are listed with no reference to the original data, so what type of change is not known. In 2012 there were 328 records changed with one or more changes, 1 change of employer, 1 change of surname, 14 changes of given name, 175 changes of position, 135 changes of salary paid, 11 changes of taxable benefits. More disturbingly, 1 where the changed row matched exactly to the original row. Not a good indicator of good data discipline.</p>

<p>In 2012, two supposed additions were in fact changes, one for position and one for employer name. This simple error will have consequences for anyone working, collaborating, or communicating with the data.</p>

<p><strong>Inconsistent Pagination</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><p>2013 disclosure has 1,000 records per page across 104 pages</p></li>
<li><p>2012 disclosure breaks up organisations (hospitals, colleges, etc.) in irregular chunks across 61 pages</p></li>
<li><p>2011 disclosure keeps most organisations on a single page, with a few broken into only two pages for a total of 15 pages</p></li>
<li><p>2010 similar to 2011 and 14 pages</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Inconsistent HTML Format</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><p>2013 and 2012 tables contain header information in thead and data in tbody</p></li>
<li><p>2011 and before tables do not contain tbody, and simply have header information in the first tr</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Inconsistent Location for those seconded to ministries</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><p>2013 has it&rsquo;s own page</p></li>
<li><p>Before it was a second table on the last page of ministries</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Other</strong></p>

<p>Inexplicably, a single record under schoolboards in 2007 has a taxable benefits of “101..92” rather than “$101.92” like the record immediately following it. Yes that&rsquo;s two decimals and no dollar sign. Inexplicably, a single record under other in 2007 has a salary paid of “$115, 448.78”. Yes, there&rsquo;s a space after the comma. Yes, these may seem like small things, but they betray a deeper malpractice. A properly validated and typed data structure would not allow this abnormalities.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pathologists Follow-up, Data From 1996 to 2013 From Ontario "Sunshine List"]]></title>
    <link href="http://alekseynp.com/2013/05/06/pathologists-follow-up-data-from-1996-to-2013-from-ontario-sunshine-list/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-06T16:31:34-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alekseynp.com/2013/05/06/pathologists-follow-up-data-from-1996-to-2013-from-ontario-sunshine-list</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a follow-up on my article, <a href="http://alekseynp.com/20-25-raise-for-ontarios-pathologists-in-201-shows-sunshine-list/">20-25% raise for Ontario’s pathologists in 2012</a>. Evolving from an explorative analysis of the 2013 Ontario Public Sector Salary Disclosure, the &ldquo;Sunshine List&rdquo;, I identified a surprising change in the packages (salary + benefits) of pathologists on the list.</p>

<p><strong>Further Analysis</strong></p>

<p>Extending the analysis backwards to 1996, the start of the “Sunshine List” we can get a more complete picture of salary changes for Ontario pathologists.</p>

<p><a href="http://alekseynp.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/pathologistsovertime.png"><img src="http://alekseynp.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/pathologistsovertime.png" alt="pathologistsovertime" /></a></p>

<p>The analysis and the visual shows that:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Since 1997, pathologist packages have increased on average 5.5% annually</p></li>
<li><p>From 1997 to 2007, packages increased 6.6% annually and exponentially which was clearly unsustainable</p></li>
<li><p>From 2007 to 2012, packages saw little to no growth</p></li>
<li><p>In 2013, there was an unprecedented, single-year growth of 22%</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Contact</strong></p>

<p>I contacted the Ontario Ministry of Health and Long-Term Care. Their media relations passed me on to the Ontario Association of Pathologists, whom I had already contacted and have yet to see a response. A sensible strategy for them would be to ignore enquiries from bloggers regardless of if they had anything to hide.</p>

<p><strong>More</strong></p>

<p>You can read more on this topic in a<a href="http://opinion.financialpost.com/2013/07/08/terence-corcoran-the-sunshine-race-to-the-top/"> piece in the Financial Post</a> which cites these findings.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
