<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Critique | Aleksey Nozdryn-Plotnicki]]></title>
  <link href="http://alekseynp.github.io/categories/critique/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alekseynp.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-14T23:29:20-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://alekseynp.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aleksey Nozdryn-Plotnicki]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[American Social Mobility, NPR, and Commentary]]></title>
    <link href="http://alekseynp.github.io/2014/03/20/american-social-mobility-npr-and-commentary/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-20T00:40:50-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alekseynp.github.io/2014/03/20/american-social-mobility-npr-and-commentary</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Regarding: <a href="http://www.npr.org/blogs/money/2014/03/18/289013884/who-had-richer-parents-doctors-or-arists">Who Had Richer Parents, Doctors Or Artists? : Planet Money : NPR</a></p>

<p>First of all, hats off to them for asking and answering important questions about modern society. The tldr; is that they ask &ldquo;Who had richer parents, journalists or people working in finance? Doctors or artists? More generally: What&rsquo;s the link between household income during childhood and job choice during adulthood?&rdquo; and based on a US government survey, they produced an answer.</p>

<p>They generate two elegant charts to illustrate their findings and I invite you to go to the article and see.</p>

<p>But something irked me about all of it and it took me some time to put my finger on it and ultimately it was the lack of extra commentary.</p>

<p>The first chart is a simple message: Doctors earn a lot more than their parents. Designers a lot less. But this isn&rsquo;t all that surprising given that we know what doctors earn quite a lot of money and designers don&rsquo;t. Even in a purely egalitarian society with 100% social mobility we would expect this. All of this tells us is that there is at least some social mobility. Not all rich doctors are born of rich doctor families.</p>

<p>The second chart is delightfully complex for journalism, but I felt even I, as a trained analyst, was struggling to get the right message out of it. Either I&rsquo;m having an off day, I think too highly of myself, or the readers are going to need some help.</p>

<p>Enter my adjustment:</p>

<p><a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/social_mobility_final.png"><img src="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/social_mobility_final.png" alt="social_mobility_final" /></a></p>

<p>I&hellip;</p>

<ul>
<li><p>&hellip; expanded the axes to include the full income distribution</p></li>
<li><p>&hellip; labeled the X=Y line for what it was</p></li>
<li><p>&hellip; added a Y=50 line to put the data into better context</p></li>
<li><p>&hellip; hand guestimated a line of best fit for the points so we could see where the United States sits</p></li>
<li><p>&hellip; made an important point about the lack of professions in the region left out of the original graphic</p></li>
</ul>


<p>An important and complicated question to answer is still missing: Nurses, for example, come of households at the 50th percentile. But is this all nurses coming from households all at the 50th percentile? Or nurses coming from households with incomes across the entire range, who on average are at the 50th percentile? If we knew the answer to that, then we would really start to learn about the potential for social mobility.</p>

<p>Ultimately they say that, &ldquo;These graphs aren&rsquo;t intended to answer broader questions about inequality and social mobility.&rdquo; But I don&rsquo;t see why they shouldn&rsquo;t be part of the debate.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Left and Right Are Important]]></title>
    <link href="http://alekseynp.github.io/2014/02/17/left-and-right-are-important/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-17T17:05:54-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alekseynp.github.io/2014/02/17/left-and-right-are-important</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The major consultancies are turning out to be a goldmine for content for demonstrating the potential for improved data visualisation design. Today&rsquo;s winner is PWC, though their error is not terribly sinful and with some effort one could probably find something worse.</p>

<p>This is a demonstration of the power and importance of left-to-right. The original violates two assumptions readers make about left-to-right:</p>

<ol>
<li><p> Things further to the right are later in time</p></li>
<li><p> Things further to the right are higher, bigger, better.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>In the original 2014 is shown to the left of 2013 and the bars are ordered high, medium, low.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.pwc.com/gx/en/asset-management/emerging-trends-real-estate/european-investment-market-forecast.jhtml">The Original</a>:</p>

<p><a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/business-prospects.gif"><img src="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/business-prospects.gif" alt="business-prospects" /></a></p>

<p>Quick answers to basic questions:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Are things good or bad? Bad. The bars make a download sloping shape.</p></li>
<li><p>Are things better or worse than last year? Hard to tell.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>What if we simply change the left-to-right ordering of everything?</p>

<p>Left-to-right changes:</p>

<p><a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/business-prospects_v2.gif"><img src="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/business-prospects_v2.gif" alt="business-prospects_v2" /></a></p>

<p>So now we at least get the impression that things are good before we start studying the labeling in detail. We can also scan across, say, the red bars in order to see how things are changing with time without having to realize that the chart&rsquo;s timeline is backwards.</p>

<p>I also experimented with a line design here:</p>

<p><a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/pwc2.png"><img src="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/pwc2.png" alt="pwc2" /></a></p>

<ul>
<li><p>Maybe the &ldquo;things are good&rdquo; message is a little muted</p></li>
<li><p>We can certainly see the trends over time, though. Generally flat, but with fewer doubters and a bit more optimists.</p></li>
<li><p>The central story of the graphic becomes the crossed lines in Business headcount. Unfortunately this is probably indicating an error in the original graphic. Scroll up and see the probably incorrect data labels</p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[KPMG's Grid of Donuts]]></title>
    <link href="http://alekseynp.github.io/2014/02/16/kpmgs-grid-of-donuts/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-16T16:04:58-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alekseynp.github.io/2014/02/16/kpmgs-grid-of-donuts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Another day, another poor visual. Apparently I have a quest to complete against bad visuals from consultancies. Today it&rsquo;s KPMG from this tweet:
<a href="https://twitter.com/KPMG/status/434401678931263488">https://twitter.com/KPMG/status/434401678931263488</a></p>

<p>A 4x4 grid of single-value donuts? Are you kidding?</p>

<p>Like <a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/2014/02/16/dubious-visuals-in-thought-leadership-from-consultancies/">last time</a>, I will show you how this is bad with simple re-design.</p>

<p>First let&rsquo;s try simply cleaning up the graphic a bit:</p>

<p><a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/BgdOBnbIAAAJgsj-2.png"><img src="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/BgdOBnbIAAAJgsj-2.png" alt="BgdOBnbIAAAJgsj-2" /></a></p>

<p>It looks better already! If I can improve your graphic by erasing the visual elements that you used to encode your data, this is a very bad sign.</p>

<p>And finally the obligatory bar-chart redesign:</p>

<p><a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/kpmg-data-and-analytics.png"><img src="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/kpmg-data-and-analytics.png" alt="kpmg data and analytics" /></a></p>

<p>Extra patterns become visible:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>EMEA generally more pessimistic than Americas, Asia-Pacific of Overall</p></li>
<li><p>EMEA substantially less impressed by More sophisticated/granular insights</p></li>
</ul>


<p>KPMG can <a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/2014/02/16/dubious-visuals-in-thought-leadership-from-consultancies/">join Accenture</a> on the list of consultancies that should practice better data visualisation, especially when generating thought leadership on the topic of data and anatlytics.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Venezuelan Bat Pie]]></title>
    <link href="http://alekseynp.github.io/2013/10/01/venezuelan-bat-pie/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-01T00:59:14-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alekseynp.github.io/2013/10/01/venezuelan-bat-pie</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Pointing out failures of the Venezuelan government can be a little too easy at times.</p>

<p>Today, points for creativity, but the 3-dimensional Venezuelan pie is an absolute technical failure.</p>

<p>Case in point, compare the yellow 12% slice to the 25% and 48% slices. The reader has no chance to use either area or angles to compare the data values, and are left simply to read the values and ignore the visual aid.</p>

<p><a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/DSC_8769.jpg"><img src="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/DSC_8769-1024x685.jpg" alt="DSC_8769" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/DSC_8768.jpg"><img src="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/DSC_8768-685x1024.jpg" alt="DSC_8768" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Small Multiples of Pies From the Economist?]]></title>
    <link href="http://alekseynp.github.io/2013/08/20/small-multiples-of-pies-from-the-economist/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-20T12:54:37-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://alekseynp.github.io/2013/08/20/small-multiples-of-pies-from-the-economist</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Really guys?</p>

<p><a href="http://www.economist.com/blogs/graphicdetail/2013/08/daily-chart-12?fsrc=rss">http://www.economist.com/blogs/graphicdetail/2013/08/daily-chart-12?fsrc=rss</a></p>

<p>Pie charts can be used to show a part-to-whole relationship with a relatively small number of parts. That is, if you have something that breaks down into 5 or so parts, then you can use a pie to show it. If you have 10 decades and they are ordinal, that is they have a natural ordering to them, then you might be tempted to do what The Economist did below&hellip; But don&rsquo;t!</p>

<p>All you have to do is try and use the chart at the top to answer simple questions like: Which is the most popular? More difficult, which is second most? How much more or less popular are the 50s vs the 80s?</p>

<p><a href="http://www.economist.com/blogs/graphicdetail/2013/08/daily-chart-12?fsrc=rss"><img src="http://cdn.static-economist.com/sites/default/files/imagecache/595-width-retina/20130824_GDC239_1190.png" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Obviously I&rsquo;m going to recommend a bar chart instead, which would have a different aspect ratio and might not work well in the space allowed by the graphic. A good alternative to a bar chart would be to put in a line in each of the charts representing the average result. I&rsquo;ve sketched it below:</p>

<p><a href="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/economist_better.png"><img src="http://alekseynp.github.io/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/economist_better-973x1024.png" alt="economist_better" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
